In this lesson, we will
go over function calling,
a new capability added to the
OpenAI API a few months ago.
We'll go over how exactly to use this,
and some tips and tricks
for getting best results.
OpenAI has fine-tuned some
of their most recent models
to accept additional
parameters for function calling.
These models are
fine-tuned to determine if it's
relevant to call one of these functions,
In this lesson, we'll use
the OpenAI SDK directly,
To walk through this example we're
going to imagine that we have a function
that we think is interesting to
provide to the language model.
And we'll go over what
interesting means later on,
because there are a bunch of
different use cases for this new parameter.
Here, we're going to define a
getCurrentWeather function.
This is an example from OpenAI themselves,
when they first
released this functionality.
This is a good example to use
because getting the current weather is
something that the language model
can't necessarily do by itself.
And so, we often want to
connect language models to functions
In this example, we hard code
the information that's returned,
but in production this
could be hitting a weather
API or some external source of knowledge.
OpenAI has exposed a new
parameter called functions through
which you can pass a list
of function definitions.
The full function definition
for the above is right here.
As you can see it's a
list and then the element
in the list there's only one because we're
only passing one
function and here it is this
JSON object with a few
different parameters.
You've got a name paramete,r and
this is the name of the function.
You've then got a description parameter,
And then, next you have
this parameter object.
And in here, there's properties.
Properties is itself
another object, and we can see
Each of these elements has a type,
string, and then, a description.
Unit is an enum, because we want it
to be either Celsius or Fahrenheit.
And so we can reflect that here.
We can also convey that the only
required parameter is location,
we're going to pass these
functions directly to the language model,
the description parameter here. And then,
And so, the language model
will use these descriptions
Any information you want the language
model to have in order to determine whether to
call a function or how to call a function
should be in the description here or here.
Let's then import the OpenAI SDK and
call the chat completion endpoint.
First, we're going to specify the model.
We're going to make
sure to specify one of the
more recent ones that has this capability.
Next, we're going to pass in
our messages defined above.
Let's run this and see what we get.
Let's look at the full response.
We can see that the message we
get back has role of assistant,
has null for content, and
instead has this function
call parameter which has two
objects, name and arguments.
Name is get current weather.
This is the same name as the
function that we passed in,
and then arguments is this JSON blob.
Let's take a closer look
at the response message.
Again, content is now empty.
And function call is this dictionary.
The arguments parameter in function
call is a JSON dictionary itself,
so we can use JSON.loads to load
this into a Python dictionary.
The arguments that it passed
back can be directly passed
into OpenAI doesn't
directly call the function.
We still have to do that ourselves.
Rather, it just tells us what
function to call, that's the name,
and what the arguments to
that function should be.
It's also worth noting that although
this is trained to return a JSON blob,
it's actually not strictly enforced.
What happens if the message that you pass
in isn't related to the function at all?
Let's try it out and
see what happens then.
Let's create a new set of messages,
this time ones that can see that the
message that's returned has content as normal,
and it doesn't have that
function call parameter.
What's going on under
the hood is that the model
is determining whether
to use a function or not.
There are additional
parameters that we can pass in
to force the model to use
or not to use a function.
Let's take a look at those.
That additional parameter is
the function call parameter.
By default, it's set to auto.
This means that the language model
chooses. This is what we've been doing so far.
There's two other modes
that we can use it in.
In the first mode, we can
force it to call a function.
This is good if we always
want to return the function,
and we'll see some use cases
for that later on in the lesson.
As you can see, because
we're using auto and we're
letting the language
model choose what to do,
here it recognizes that it
doesn't need to call the function
and so it's responding as
before with role and content only.
Another mode for function
call that we can use is none.
This forces the language model not
to use any of the functions provided.
In this example it doesn't
really matter because the
content high doesn't need
the function call anyways.
But what happens when the
messages should call function here?
It should call the get
current weather function.
But when we look down, we still
see the usual role and content.
That's because we're forcing it
not to call the function. And so,
The final option for the function call
parameter is forcing it to call a function.
Let's see how to do that.
And if we look at the response we can
see that in fact we do get this function
call object returned and it's got name
get current weather with some arguments.
Just for fun let's see what
happens if we pass in a message
that doesn't need to call the
function but we force it to.
So here, it's making up
San Francisco, California.
If we run it again, it keeps on
calling San Francisco, California.
Some final things to note.
First, the functions
themselves and the descriptions count
against the token usage
limit that you pass to OpenAI.
If we comment out
functions and function call,
we can see that prompt
tokens goes down to 15.
In this particular example,
the function definition
and the function description
are taking up a lot of the tokens.
This is important to note because
OpenAI models have a token limit on them.
And so, as you're constructing
your messages to pass to OpenAI,
Finally, let's now take a look at how you
can pass some of these function calls and
the results of actually doing the
function calls back into the language model.
This is important because
oftentimes you want to use the
language model to
determine what function to call,
then run that function,
but then pass it back into
the language model to
get a final response.
We'll then take this message and
we'll append it to our list of messages.
We can then simulate calling
the getCurrentWeather function
with the arguments that
the language model provides.
Let's save this to a variable and
then we can append a new message to the
list representing the response
from the function that we just call.
We do this with a new type of message.
Notice that it has a
role equal to function.
This is used to convey
to the language model
that it's the response
of calling a function.
We then also pass in the name,
which is the name of the function,
and a content variable, which we
can set up equal to observation,
which we calculated above.
If we then call the language
model with this list of messages,
we can see that the language model
takes the response of the observation
and converts it into a nice
natural language response.
The current weather in
Boston is 72 degrees
Fahrenheit with a
sunny and windy forecast.
That's all for this lesson
where we introduced OpenAI function
calling and how to use it
with the OpenAI SDK directly.
In the next lessons, we're gonna
cover how to combine this with langchain
primitives to make it easier and
faster to use this functionality.